Finding Aid for National Organization for Women, Michigan Conference Records, 1969-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Alicia Perez-Banuet, 1972-1996
  - Topical File
    Topical File (1972-1994; 2.3 linear ft.) includes information on many of the issues and activities the Michigan NOW conference has been involved with throughout the years. This accession expands upon many of the coalitions present in the Margot Duley-Morrow subseries. However, two topics (Abortion and ERA) and one committee (PAC) dominate the materials in this series. The material on abortion and the People's Campaign for Choice (PCC), the coalition formed by Michigan NOW to lobby for the retention of tax-payer funding for abortions, is very extensive and highlights the amount of work involved in that tumultuous battle. Included among the materials are a large amount of clippings from Michigan press, legislative information including House Bills and Senate Journals highlighting the activity in the state capitol, medical studies and reports, financial studies and reports on the cost of Medicaid abortions versus raising a child on Medicaid, and materials collected from the opposition Right-To-Life Initiative. The material on the ERA focuses mainly on attempts to lobby government in order to secure an extension to ratify the amendment. Because the ERA had already been ratified in Michigan, much of the material is based on the national effort and contains information about how the Michigan conference could work to support other states working towards ratification. In addition to the topics of abortion and the ERA, the Political Action Committee (PAC) material makes up a large portion of this series. The Candidate Questionnaires, no longer seen as a valuable source of information about a candidate, provide an interesting look into the ideologies of past political candidates from House Representatives to Governor. Along with these records are endorsement lists, election results, and other miscellaneous material that detail the importance of political elections to activist organizations such as NOW.
    - Abortion
      - Clippings, 1980-1988 (Box 11)
      - Committee to remove Judge Halstead, 1982 (Box 11)
      - Facts and Figures, Michigan, 1978-1981 (Box 11)
      - Lansing Area Advocates for Choice (LAAC), 1988-1989 (Box 11)
      - Legislation
        - Medicaid Funding (H.B. 4007), 1985 (Box 11)
        - Medicaid Funding (H.B. 5639), 1986 (Box 11)
      - Medicaid Funding, 1978-1981 (Box 11)
      - Medicaid Funding, 1983-1987 (Box 11)
      - Medicaid Funding, 1985 (Box 11)
      - Medicaid Funding, 1988 (Box 11)
      - Medical Aspects of Abortion, 1979 (Box 11)
      - People's Campaign for Choice
        - Administrative, 1987 (Box 11)
        - Media Coordinator Materials, 1987-1988 (Box 11)
          (includes photographs of a signed petition for a referendum election to reject the act that would prohibit tax-funded welfare abortions)
        - Miscellaneous, 1985-1987 (Box 11)
        - Outreach Committee, 1987 (Box 11)
        - Proposal A Press Material, 1987-1989 (Box 11)
        - Training Material, 1988 (Box 11)
      - Pro-Choice Conference Planning Material (Box 11)
      - Right-to-Life Initiative
        - Clippings, 1986-1990 (Box 11)
        - Miscellaneous, 1985-1990 (Box 11)
        - Petition Drive, 1986-1987 (Box 11)
    - Clinic Escort Training, 1987-1989 (Box 11)
    - Education Task Force, 1983 (Box 11)
    - ERA (Equal Rights Amendment)
      - Correspondence, 1975-1979 (Box 11)
      - Extension Resolution, 1977-1978 (Box 11)
      - Michigan ERAmerica, 1977-1981 (Box 11)
      - Miscellaneous, 1978-1979 (Box 11)
      - Opposition Clippings, 1965-1979 (Box 11)
      - Rescission, 1979-1980 (Box 11)
      - Strategy, 1977-1980 (Box 12)
      - Walk-A-Thon Material, 1978-1979 (Box 12)
    - Detroit News, Sex Discrimination Case, 1977 (Box 12)
    - Fetal Drug Dependency Legislation (H.B. 4007), 1987 (Box 12)
    - Lesbian/Gay Rights, circa 1980 (Box 12)
    - Legislative Activity, 1980-1982 (Box 12)
    - Loehr, Davidson (People's Church) writings, 1987-1989 (Box 12)
    - March for Women's Equality/Women's Lives, 1989 (Box 12)
    - Medical Self-Determination Legislation (H.B. 4176-4177), 1987 (Box 12)
    - MHSAA (Michigan High School Athletic Association) Complaint, 1983 (Box 12)
    - Michigan Coalition for Fair Implementation of Block Grants, 1981-1982 (Box 12)
    - Michigan Coalition for Parental Leave, 1987 (Box 12)
    - Michigan Welfare Reform Coalition
      - Minutes and Agenda's, 1982-1983 (Box 12)
      - Miscellaneous, 1981-1982 (Box 12)
    - Michigan Women's Assembly
      - Organizational Platform, 1984 (Box 12)
      - Organizational Platform, 1986-1988 (Box 12)
      - Organizational Platform, 1988-1990 (Box 12)
    - Michigan Women's Commission, 1986 (Box 12)
    - No Fault Divorce Legislation (H.B. 4098), 1981 (Box 12)
    - Parental Leave Legislation (H.B. 4504), 1986-1987 (Box 12)
    - Pay Equity
      - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 12)
      - Pay Equity Network, 1987-1988 (Box 12)
    - (PEER) Project on Equal Education Rights Program, 1983 (Box 12)
    - (PAC) Political Action Committee
      - Elections
        - Candidate Questionnaires, 1982 (Box 12)
        - Endorsements, Candidate Lists, Election Results, 1982 (Box 12)
        - Miscellaneous, 1982 (Box 12)
        - Candidate Questionnaires, 1984 (Box 12)
        - Endorsements, Candidate Lists, Election Results, 1984 (Box 12)
        - Candidate Questionnaires (Representatives, Districts 1-50), 1986 (Box 12)
        - Candidate Questionnaires (Representatives, Districts 51-110), 1986 (Box 12)
        - Candidate Questionnaires (Senators, Districts 1-36), 1986 (Box 12)
        - Miscellaneous, 1986 (Box 12)
        - Candidate Questionnaires, Correspondence, Endorsements, 1988 (Box 12)
        - Candidate Questionnaires, Candidate Information, 1992 (Box 12)
        - Endorsement Lists, Correspondence, 1992 (Box 12)
      - Miscellaneous, circa 1981-1984 (Box 13)
      - National PAC, 1983-1986 (Box 13)
      - 20/200 Club, 1981-1982 (Box 13)
    - Pope John Paul II Visit, 1987 (Box 13)
    - Sexual Harassment Legislation (H.B. 4407), 1978-1981 (Box 13)
    - Spousal Rape, 1978-1981 (Box 13)
    - Surrogate Parenting Legislation (S.B. 228), 1987-1988 (Box 13)
    - Title X, 1987 (Box 13)
    - Visitation Legislation (H.B. 5028), 1987 (Box 13)
    - YWCA Public Affairs Committee, 1986-1990 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence
    Correspondence (1972-1980, 0.3 linear ft.) includes both incoming and outgoing correspondence from and to various individuals and organizations involved with Michigan NOW and its activities.
    - 1972-1980, 9 folders (Box 13)
  - Chapter Newsletters
    Chapter Newsletters (1981-1989, 0.2 linear ft.) includes a heavy concentration of newsletters published between 1986 and 1989 from several of the local chapters active in the state. The continuity of the newsletters is very sporadic and incomplete, however, like the files of newsletters found in the first NOW (box 8-9) accession they provide pertinent information about NOW events and attitudes on the local, state, and nationwide level.
    - Ann Arbor, Battle Creek, Big Rapids, 1987-1988 (Box 13)
    - Mid, 1987-1988 (Box 13)
    - North Oakland County/Oakland University, 1986-1989 (Box 13)
    - Oakland County, 1987-1988 (Box 13)
    - Western Wayne County, 1987-1988 (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous Chapters, 1981-1988 (Box 13)
  - Macomb County NOW
    Macomb County NOW (1977-1982, 0.2 linear ft.) includes press releases, meeting minutes, agendas, and correspondence relating to the activities of this local chapter. Much of the correspondence is directed towards, or written by, Doris Little, chapter president from 1981 to 1982. Material of interest includes a large folder containing the details of planning a "take back the night" (march against violence towards women) rally in Macomb County and a collection of photographs contained in the Chapter Activities (1981) folder that document an ERA rally at which Carol King was the speaker. King served as Macomb County NOW president, Michigan NOW president (1979-1980), and served as a National Board Member following her term as state conference president. This small collection of files compliments the Doris Little, Macomb County NOW subgroup from the first accession (box 7).
    - Press Releases, 1977-1981 (Box 13)
    - Newsletter Editor Packet, 1979 (Box 13)
    - Chapter Activities, 1981 (Box 13)
      (includes photographs of Carol King, 1979-80 Michigan NOW President and later a National NOW Board Member, speaking at an ERA rally)
    - Take Back the Night, 1981 (Box 13)
    - Young Feminist of the Year Award, 1981 (Box 13)
    - Chapter Activities, 1982 (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 13)
  - Administrative Files
    Administrative Files (1976-1990, 0.4 linear ft.) are scattered and inconsistent files that include minutes from state conventions and state coordinating council (SCC) meetings, leadership and chapter lists, issues and agendas, events, by-laws, guidelines and other records documenting the operations of the organization.
    - Miscellaneous, 1976-1990 (Box 14)
      (includes photographs of newly elected officers of Michigan NOW, presumably for 1981-82, with Margot Duley-Morrow-President and Nancy Hall-Administrative V.P.; also 1 photograph of Michigan NOW members posing with Helen Milliken at ERA rally in Washington DC, 1981)
    - Legislative Issues, 1977 (Box 14)
    - State Coordinating Council (SCC), 1977-1978 (Box 14)
    - Chapter and Officer Lists, 1977-1978 (Box 14)
    - Resignations, 1978-1980 (Box 14)
    - Great Lakes Regional NOW Conference (Ann Arbor), 1979-1980 (Box 14)
    - Hotline Newsletter, 1979-1981 (Box 14)
    - Resolutions, 1979-1982 (Box 14)
    - State Conference Planning Committee, 1982 (Box 14)
    - Bylaws, 1982-1988 (Box 14)
    - Membership Processing Manual and Policies/Guidelines Manual, 1986 (Box 14)
    - National NOW, 1986-1988 (Box 14)
    - Policy Manual, 1987 (Box 14)
    - Hotline Newsletter, 1989-1990 (Box 14)
  - Officer Files
    Officer Files (1977-1988, 0.6 linear ft.) include materials taken from officer binders and placed in folders. The majority of the files are from individuals who served as Michigan NOW conference secretary and reflect the types of material they would have collected in order to document the activities of the organization, including administrative materials such as leadership lists, SCC meeting minutes, newsletters, and correspondence.
    - Drinan, Rhonda, State Chapter Developer, 1977 (Box 14)
    - Frost-Welmers, Nan, State Coordinator, 1977 (Box 14)
    - Moore, Loretta, State Legislative Coordinator, 1977 (Box 14)
    - Zebko, Nancy, Secretary, 1978-1979; 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Smiley, Monica, Secretary, 1981-1982 (Box 14)
    - Unidentified, 1982 (Box 14)
    - Parshall, Maxine, Secretary, 1985-1986; 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Franz, Cheryl, Secretary, 1986-1988; 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Governance, 1979-1996
    Governance, 1979-1996 series deals with the activities of the formal state structure in the 1980s and 1990s. The records include: amended bylaws; meeting minutes for the annual state conference, State Coordinating Council and Executive Committee; leadership lists and the Federal tax exemption, derived through the national organization. There is also information on related organizations: NOW, Inc. and the Great Lakes Region NOW.
    - Bylaws, 1989-1994 (Box 15)
    - Executive Committee, 1990-1994 (Box 15)
    - Leadership Lists, 1979-1992 (Box 15)
    - Related Organizations
      - Great Lakes Region NOW, 1983-1996 (Box 15)
      - NOW, Inc.
        - History (Box 15)
        - Resolutions, 1994 (Box 15)
        - State Coordinators, 1990; 1994 (Box 15)
    - State Conference, 1985-1995 (Box 15)
    - State Coordinating Council, 1984-1994 (Box 15)
    - Tax Exemption, NOW, 1979 (Box 15)
  - Administration, 1979-1994
    Administration, 1979-1994 series contains records on the operations and organizational activities of Michigan NOW including: chapter development, correspondence, financial reports, membership, publications, and public relations. The Events subseries and Task Force subseries reflect the variety of activist efforts undertaken by Michigan NOW over two decades.
    - Chapter Development
      - Awards questionnaires, 1977-1978; 1988-1989 (Box 15)
      - Organizational materials, 1989-1991 (Box 15)
    - Clippings, 1987-1994 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1986; 1987; 1990-1991 (Box 15)
    - Events
      - Field Organizing Training, 1991 (Box 15)
      - Medical Summit Meeting, 1988 (Box 15)
      - Now Has A Heart Party, 1981-1985 (Box 15)
      - Rally for Choice, 1989 (Box 15)
      - Silent Witness, 1994 (Box 15)
    - Financial Reports, 1983-1985 (Box 15)
    - Fundraising, 1990-1992 (Box 15)
    - History (Box 15)
    - Membership, 1979-1980; 1991 (Box 15)
    - Operations, 1985-1987 (Box 15)
    - Photographs, 1980-1990 (Box 15)
    - Publications
      - Feminist Songs (Box 16)
      - Michigan NOW Hot Line, 1977-1996 (Box 16)
      - Michigan NOW Times, 1991 (Box 16)
      - Speeches (Box 16)
    - Task Forces
      - Bridge House, 1986 (Box 16)
      - Comparable Worth Task Force, 1981-1984 (Box 16)
      - Domestic Violence, 1976-1979 (Box 16)
      - Education, 1993 (Box 16)
      - ERA Ratification, 1982-1984; 1994 (Box 16)
      - Lesbian/Gay Rights Task Force, 1993 (Box 16)
      - Reproductive Rights
        - Michigan Alliance for Choice, 1991-1992 (Box 16)
        - Pregnancy Counseling and False Clinics, 1986 (Box 16)
        - Reproductive Rights Task Force, 1990-1993 (Box 16)
      - Sexual Harassment, 1992 (Box 16)
      - Violence against Women Task Force, 1993 (Box 16)
      - Women in Prison Task Force, 1990 (Box 16)
  - Lynn Hierholzer, president files, 1990-1993
    Lynn Hierholzer, president's file, 1990-1993, a native of Hale, was editor of the statewide newsletter, and president of the Michigan NOW PAC. Before becoming state president in 1991, Hierholzer served as Administrative Vice President during which time she developed job descriptions for committees and task forces. Her organizational skills made a strong impact on the organization, particularly in the area of communications with the membership and administration of "Michigan NOW Times".
    - Administration
      - Clippings (Box 16)
      - Correspondence, 1991-1993 (Box 16)
      - Daily activity journal, 1991 (Box 16)
      - Policies, 1990-1992 (Box 16)
      - Press Releases, 1991-1992 (Box 16)
      - YWCA office, 1991 (Box 16)
    - Officers
      - Action Vice President, 1992-1993 (Box 16)
      - Administrative Vice President, 1993 (Box 16)
      - Legislative Vice President, 1990-1992 (Box 16)
      - Membership Vice President, 1992-1993 (Box 16)
      - Treasurer, 1991-1992 (Box 16)
    - Topical
      - Civil Rights (Box 17)
      - Economic Justice/Employment (Box 17)
      - Education (Box 17)
      - Equal Rights Amendment (Box 17)
      - Michigan Women's Assembly, 1988-1994; 4 folders (Box 17)
      - Racial Diversity (Box 17)
      - Reproductive Rights, 3 folders (Box 17)
        (includes Michigan Choice Focus Group transcripts)
  - Gloria Woods, president files, 1987-1996
    Gloria Woods, president's file, 1987-1996 series contains records that span her state presidency, 1993-1995, and several years before and after her tenure. She was particularly interested in Public Relations and prepared a Public Relations Guide for the Michigan NOW Chapters in 1992. The organization's web site, http://www.michnow.org (accessed 5-10-05) was developed with her support in 1996. Woods, a resident of Bay City, began her activities in the Saginaw NOW chapter from the time the chapter was organized. She served as chapter president, 1987-1989. Involved in the Peoples Campaign for Choice, she was the Saginaw Chapter spokesperson, participating in interviews, news shows, and programs on such issues as abortion, Federal and State legislation, violence against women, sexual harassment, among others. Her Michigan Now activities included member of MI NOW PAC, 1987-1989; Nominating Committee member and 1991 Chair; Public Relations Committee member and 1991 Chair; Task Force on Racial Diversity; Special Committee on Sexual Harassment.
    - Administration
      - Correspondence, 1993-1996 (Box 17)
      - Fundraising (Box 17)
      - Grievance, 1991-1993 (Box 17)
      - Legislation, 1992-1994 (Box 17)
      - Personnel, 1994-1995 (Box 17)
      - State Coordinating Council, 1994-1995 (Box 17)
    - Chapter Newsletters, 1986-1995; 2 folders
      - Allegan (Box 17)
      - Ann Arbor (Box 17)
      - Battle Creek (Box 17)
      - Bay Area (Box 17)
      - Detroit (Box 17)
      - Downriver (Box 17)
      - Flint (Box 17)
      - Grand Rapids (Box 17)
      - Jackson (Box 17)
      - Kalamazoo (Box 17)
      - Lansing (Box 17)
      - Livingston County (Box 17)
      - Macomb County (Box 17)
      - Oakland County (Box 17)
      - North Oakland (Box 17)
      - Saginaw (Box 17)
      - Three Rivers (Box 17)
      - Western Wayne County (Box 17)
    - Public Relations
      - Clippings (Box 17)
      - Press Releases, 1993-1995 (Box 18)
      - Public Relations Guide, 1992 (Box 18)
      - Website, 1996 (Box 18)
    - Topical
      - Abortion Waiting Period, 1994 (Box 18)
      - Campaign to Promote Responsibility, 1994 (Box 18)
      - Child Custody, 1994 (Box 18)
      - Child Support, 1995 (Box 18)
      - Racial Diversity, 1993 (Box 18)
      - Welfare, 1995 (Box 18)
  - Michigan NOW PAC, 1979-1994
    Michigan NOW PAC, 1979-1994 series contains the records of the separately incorporated lobbying arm of Michigan NOW. Records of candidate questionnaires and endorsements comprise the largest portion of this series, and is a continuation of a similar series in Box 12. Also included are the "Elect a Woman for Change" campaign, 1992-1994, and organizational records.
    - Administration
      - Correspondence, 1989-1992 (Box 18)
      - Emily's List Comments, 1990 (Box 18)
      - Fundraising, 1990-1994 (Box 18)
      - Lobbying Reports and Registration, 1983-1990 (Box 18)
      - Minutes, 1989-1991; 1994 (Box 18)
      - Official PAC Manual, 1990 (Box 18)
      - Shafer, Ann, 1916-1991 (Box 18)
      - SCC Reports, 1990-1992 (Box 18)
      - Treasury Reports, 1985; 1990-1992 (Box 18)
    - Elect A Woman For Change, 1992; 1994 (Box 18)
    - Endorsements, 1980-1992
      (includes Judicial, House, and Senate)
      - 1990
        - Candidate Questionnaires, 5 folders (Box 18)
        - Judicial Questionnaires (Box 18)
      - 1991 (Box 18)
      - 1992
        - Candidate Questionnaires, 5 folders (Box 18)
        - Judicial Questionnaires, 2 folders (Box 19)
      - 1994
        - Candidate Questionnaires, 2 folders (Box 19)
        - Correspondence (Box 19)
        - Endorsements (Box 19)
  - Legislative Committee, 1976-1994
    Legislative Committee, 1976-1994 series contains a number of bills supported by Michigan NOW along with other records that deal with the committee activities including minutes, reports, and topical issues. Documentation accompanying some of the bills include analysis and testimony from Michigan NOW members before the legislative committees.
    - Legislative Issues, 1990
      - Abortion articles and data (Box 19)
      - HB 5499 (Box 19)
        (Interference with health care access)
      - Position Recommendations, 1990 (Box 19)
    - Legislation, Bills Supported, 1993-1994
      - HB 4064, 1993 (Box 19)
        (amend Child Custody Act)
      - HB 4135-4138, 4803, 1993 (Box 19)
      - HB 4141, 1993 (Box 19)
        (extension of funding for medical and child care for former ADC mothers)
      - HB 4325, 1993 (Box 19)
        (domestic violence)
      - HB 4499, 1993 (Box 19)
        (Women and Minority Business Utilization Act)
      - HB 4430 4518, 1993 (Box 19)
        (recovery for injuries caused by act of sexual abuse)
      - HB 4603, 1993 (Box 19)
        (extension of funding for medical care for former ADC mothers)
      - HB 4618, 1993 (Box 19)
        (legal access to health care facilities)
      - HB 4696, 1993 (Box 19)
        (equal participation for women-and minority-owned businesses)
      - HB 4741, 1993 (Box 19)
        (health care reform)
      - HB 4806, 1993 (Box 19)
        (restriction on release of vehicle registration data)
      - HB 5220, 1993 (Box 19)
        (child support payments)
      - HB 4024, 1994 (Box 19)
        (witness against spouse)
      - HB 4120, 1994 (Box 19)
        (plumbing fixtures in public buildings)
      - HB 4177, 1994 (Box 19)
        (child pornography)
      - HB 4385, 1994 (Box 19)
        (pay equity)
      - HB 4430, 1994 (Box 19)
        (family sexual abuse, incest)
      - HB 4485, 1994 (Box 19)
        (laboratory personnel licensure)
      - HB 4561, 1994 (Box 19)
        (heirs out of wedlock)
      - HB 4757, 1994 (Box 19)
        (child abuse and neglect reporting)
      - HB 4989 4991, 1994 (Box 19)
        (midwifery and insurance coverage)
      - HB 5061, 1994 (Box 19)
        (Michigan Campus Sexual Assault Information)
      - HB 5264, 1994 (Box 19)
        (ADC family cap)
      - HB 5296, 1994 (Box 19)
      - HB 5301, 1994 (Box 19)
        (prohibit abortions for gender selection)
      - HB 5804, 1994 (Box 19)
        (personal protection order)
    - Legislative Alerts, 1978-1981; 1986; 1994 (Box 19)
    - Topical
      - Child Support Guidelines, 1986 (Box 19)
      - Choice and Medical Funding, 1976-1980 (Box 19)
      - Domestic Violence, 1994 (Box 19)
      - Family Violence Hotline, 1994 (Box 19)
      - Honigman, State Representative David, 1984-1986 (Box 19)
        (rationale for change of position on abortion)
      - Midwifery, 1993 (Box 19)
      - Piotowski vs. Piotowski, 1993-1994 (Box 19)
        (use of maiden name)
      - Social Security, 1978 (Box 19)
Related Materials
The Bentley Library also has separate collections of records for Patricia Hill Burnett, Monica Smiley and Marian McCracken, and for the Western Wayne and Oakland County Chapters of NOW. There are also records for Michigan Womens Assembly, an organization closely related with Michigan NOW.